Manuel Gonzalez

Senior Android Developer

CONTACT

E-mail: manuelrg88@gmail.com

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/manuel-gonzalez-25444217a/

GitHub: https://github.com/charromax

Mobile: (54) 9 341 722 8537

SUMMARY

A Senior Android Developer with a passion for IoT and AI projects. Android specialist with solid knowledge of Kotlin Multiplatform, Electronics and Arduino. Creative and enthusiastic about technology that makes people's lives easier, not harder.

SKILLS

Languages and Frameworks: C++, Kotlin, Java, Jetpack Compose

Image loading: Glide, Coil

DI: Dagger/Hilt, Koin

Networking: Retrofit, KTor

Testing: Mockito, Mockk, Robolectric, JUnit4

OS & Platforms: MacOS, zsh

DBMS: SQLite, GraphQL, Firebase Realtime Database, Firestore

SCM, Build, CI/CD: GitHub CI/CD

Methodologies and Architectures: Test-Driven Development (TDD), Design Patterns, SOLID, Clean Architecture, MVP, MVI, MVVM, Scrum methodology.

EDUCATION

- Escuela San Pablo 2073 2005 Electronics
- Instituto Brigadier Lopez 2020 Software Development

EMPLOYMENT HISTORY

Freelance, Android developer 2020 - 2021

Freelanced for a little over a year for various companies in the food industry while honing my skills as a professional android developer, working to help businesses reconvert as the pandemic demanded more online storefronts to meet restrictions and user demand.

Activities and responsibilities:

- Online restaurant menu UI using XML and RecyclerView
- Restaurant recommendation system based on network requests and GPS location using Google Maps
 API
- Implementation of REST endpoints using Volley
- Bug fixing

Technologies: Android, MVP architecture, XML views, RecyclerView, Java, Volley, GitLab, Maps API, Scrum, Glide.

Nimble, Android Developer 2021 - 2023

Nimble is a company specializing in information technology services based in Los Angeles, California. I worked at Nimble as a Software Engineer for 3 years, starting out as a Trainee but quickly made my way into a full blown Android Developer in less than a year.

Some relevant projects during Nimble:

Bambino Sitters, Android developer

Bambino is a platform that connects families and babysitters US-wide. Their motto is "It takes a village to raise a child" and it was the #1 babysitting app in the AppStore for many years, during

my time in the company we had some 5000+ users in the USA. My primary activities involved updating legacy code and architecture to meet moderns standards, as half of the code was Java and MVP, implementation of Retrofit to sunset Volley as the primary networking library, as well as developing new features such as contact synchronization, hashing and securely storing the contact list using Andoid's Encryption API for later comparison with server's contact list. Also, I undertook the implementation of Sitter and User profile pages, as well as sitter search page. All of our screens were implemented as RecyclerViews to provide a smoother scrolling experience.

Activities and responsibilities:

- Implementation of new features according to Miro designs.
- Distribution to testers using Firebase App Distribution.
- Code reviews.
- Legacy code update from MVP to MVVM.
- RxJava migration to Coroutines and LiveData.
- Volley migration to Retrofit.
- Bug fixing.
- Custom XML views to comply with IOS look and feel.
- Home page redesign implementation.
- User and Babysitter profile page implementation.
- BabySitter search page implementation.
- Stripe SDK implementation for payments.

Technologies: Android, Java, Kotlin, MVP, MVVM, XML views, Retrofit, Coroutines, LiveData, RxJava, Volley, GitHub Actions, Scrum, Stripe SDK, Glide.

Red Bull Wings for Life, Android Developer

Red Bull's run tracking app, specifically tailored to support their annual Wings for Life Marathon, was fully developed using Kotlin and Jetpack Compose which greatly improved the team's velocity and overall developing experience. My biggest undertaking was a complete revamping and centralization of their permission request system, something the app heavily relied on to be able to track the user's location, to this end we developed a 5 step user onboarding flow, complete with animations and background video which was optimised to work in lower memory devices as well as higher end ones. I also participated in minor redesign implementations in the user's profile page and run tracking screens. I also spearheaded the addition of unit tests for UI components using Robolectric and JUnit4.

Activities and responsibilities:

- Implementation of REST API endpoints.
- Bug fixing and Crashlytics reports tracking and fixing.
- User onboarding flow with animations in Jetpack Compose.

- Permission request system revamping as part of onboarding flow using Accompanist library.
- User profile page redesign implementation.
- Implementation of composables unit tests using Robolectric and JUnit4.
- Code reviews.

Technologies: Android, Kotlin, Jetpack Compose, Clean architecture, layer modules, MVI, Figma, Retrofit, Accompanist, Maps API, Robolectric, JUnit4, Coil

Applaudo Studios, Android developer 2024 - present

Applaudo studios is a software factory based in El Salvador with numerous government-related projects as well as private clients. In my case, I worked with their Volaris team, a low–cost Mexican airline, upgrading their web-app into a full native Android Application in a large team of around 23 developers. My top contribution this past year was the implementation of their flight reservation management screen, offline-first with a list of added bookings and booking details. Also contributed heavily to fixing bugs to reach the goal of delivering the first version of the app which will be available to users within the next month, this included QA work as well as localisation verification.

Activities and responsibilities:

- Implementation of passenger list screen where users start their check-in process
- Travel document scanning system using MRZ scanner SDK as well as manual document entry pages for user check-in flow
- General bug Fixing to reach MVP, either QA or Crashlytics reported
- Offline-first Manage my Flight module implementation where users can see and make changes to their bookings using Room and Retrofit with a Repository + DataSource pattern.
- Code reviews
- Manual QA of localisation strings using Firebase RemoteConfig

Technologies: Android, Jetpack Compose, MVI with Reducer pattern, feature modules, Clean architecture, Bitbucket, Figma, Firebase Remote Config, Offline-first design with Room, MRZ scanner SDK, Coil.

KMM Developer - Personal projects highlight

Dec 2024 - PRESENT

KBuscaminas is an ongoing Compose Multiplatform app targeting Android, IOS and Desktop; inspired by the classic Minesweeper game. The project is modularized by feature and follows Clean Architecture principles to ensure scalability and maintainability.

Role: Kmm Developer

Stack:

- Compose Multiplatform: Modern UI development for Android and other platforms.
- Kotlin Multiplatform: Shared logic and models.
- Dependency Injection: Koin
- Database: Room and SQLite.
- State Management: Jetpack Compose and AndroidX Lifecycle.
- Testing: MockK and Kotest.
- CI/CD pipeline through Github Actions.

See Release section on github for executable files

Link: https://github.com/charromax/Buscaminas